Look up.
来，往上看，往上看
Some people stop producing enough tears
有些人过了三十岁呢
when they pass thirty.
他眼泪的分泌可能就会不够
Tears are produced
那我们眼泪分泌呢
for two reasons.
通常有两个方面
Firstly,
第一个方面呢
the eyes need moistening.
就是你眼膜本身就需要这些眼泪
Secondly,
另外一个方面
when you get emotional
可能就是你的情绪所产生的
Iike crying
比如说你想哭啊
or you're moved by something.
或者是特别感动的时候
Good.
好
Is it serious?
会不会很严重？
No.
不会
I'll prescribe some eye drops.
我开一些药给你
Take them and come back
你回去点，然后下个礼拜…
for another check
礼拜一下午，好不好
next Monday afternoon, OK?
再来做一次检查
I put a personal ad in the newspaper.
我在报上注销了一则征婚启事
I know it's hard to believe.
你一定不相信
Call it a momentary slip then.
一念之间吧！
Besides, who knows?
而且，谁知道
Maybe I'll find happiness.
说不定以后就是幸福快乐的日子
I've got over a hundred calls
三天来
in three days.
我收到了一百多通电话
Some of them asked
他们有些人会要求
to see my picture.
先看看我的照片
I said to them,
我说
I didn't ask to see theirs so
我没有要求看你们的照片
they shouldn't ask to see mine either.
所以你也不应该看我的
It's fair.
很公平！
I don't tell them I'm a doctor either.
我也不说我是医生
Anyway, I've already quit my job.
反正我已经辞掉医院的工作了
What made you decide to put up
你怎么会想到说
a personal ad to look for a husband?
用征婚这个来挑老公？
I couldn't think of anything better.
我就想不出更好的方法
Then I thought...
然后我觉得…
But you're not...
可是你长得…
... you're not bad looking.
可是你长得不丑啊！
You must be very popular.
应该还是有很多男孩子来追求你
You didn't find anyone
那些都不…
suitable?
不满意？
I don't want someone
我不想在我原来的环境里面
from my circle.
找一个适合的人
And I feel that
然后我又觉得
I can't be on my own for now.
我暂时不能一个人
What did you say?
怎么样，你说什么？
I can't be on my own.
我不能一个人
You can't be on your own?
不能一个人？
You mentioned your circle...
你说环境
What do you do?
你是做什么工作的？现在！
I've just quit.
我刚辞掉我的工作
I used to work in a hospital.
原来在医院上班
You worked in a hospital?
在医院上班
Why did you quit?
辞掉原因是？
I wanted some changes in my life.
就是想换一种生活的方式
Changes?
换一种生活的方式
Have you had boyfriends?
有交过男朋友吗？
Yes.
嗯！
How many?
几个？
Four.
四个
How long was the longest relationship?
最长的多久？最短的多久？
How long?
在一起的时间
Over three years.
三年多
The shortest?
最短的呢？
Over a year.
一年多
Could I ask something
如果我问再深入的问题
more personal?
你愿意回答吗？
It depends.
看看呀！
Hello.
喂
Nice to meet you.
小姐，你好
Nice to meet you, too.
你好
My name's Wang. Wang Chao-ming.
我姓王，王朝明
Yes, I know.
我知道
My friends call me Wang Chao.
因为我同事同学都叫我王朝
Because Wang Chao means
因为…因为我名字王朝嘛
the "Royal Soldier".
王朝明嘛
So they call me Wang Chao.
人家都叫我王朝马汉
Do you get it?
我就是王朝，对不对？
Do you mind me chewing betel nut?
我在吃槟榔，你不介意吧？
I wouldn't say I would but...
也不能说不介意啦！可是…
I'm sorry.
那不好意思
I smoke as well.
那因为我本身吃槟榔
You have to keep chewing.
就是你不能停就是了
You can't stop, can you?
你一直要吃，是不是？
No, no.
没有，没有
I can stop.
不吃也可以啊！
If you don't like it, I can stop.
如果说你介意的话
I'll just spit it out.
我可以把它吐掉都可以
Is it OK?
那可以吗？
It's OK. You keep chewing.
没关系啦，你吃！
In that case...
这样子，那我就吃！
So, Mr. Wang,
王先生，听说你…
you say that
你说你是在那个
you work in a PC factory?
PC的工厂做事是不是？
Yes, it's an industrial job.
对，因为是属于工业方面
I cut PC boards.
整片那个有没有，一个板子有没有
One after another.
一块一块
Each sheets is cut down the line.
把整个板子裁出去
Mr. Wang, I wonder...
王先生，不晓得你这样的工作
...how much do you make from your work?
一个月的那个收入是多少钱？
My pay?
收入？
Around NT$30,000
因为我那边工作收入
per month.
一个月差不多三万多块钱
It's not a lot.
多也不是很多，少也不会很少
But it's enough to survive.
还可以过的去啦！还可以养…
Enough to keep a roof over my head.
那三餐的话不成问题啦
Definitely enough!
可以！可以！
But is it enough to support a wife?
可是，要养老婆
Of course it is.
那养老婆也可以呀
I can work extra time.
因为我本身的话我可以加班呀
For my wife...
就是说，我为我老婆
I'd work extra time. I would!
我可以拼命地加班，都可以呀！
But...
可是你加班的话就
you can't do it every day.
你不能天天加班呀！
You can't cope with it...
人的体力…
And you'll have no time for your wife.
而且你就没时间陪老婆
Yes, I will.
还是有啊
Because I won't work
因为我加班的时间
until very late.
我不会加到三更半夜
I won't, right?
我不会呀！
Three hours extra
我加班最多顶多
at most.
加三个小时就好了
You said you've had many blind dates?
你上次说你相过亲很多次？
Yes, so many blind dates.
对，我相亲相过不少次
But none of them was successful.
相那么多次亲，不过很漏气
Is that...?
不是
Do you understand?
你听懂吗？听懂吗？可以吗？
Not successful, right? But...
漏气，对不对？但是…
Failures, I would say...
很失败，有没有？
What?
什么？
Nothing, you just spat on my face.
就是，你讲话都喷口水在我…
Really?
这样子是吗？
It's OK.
没关系…
I'm so sorry.
那很不好意思，不好意思
I've had a lot of girlfriends,
因为我本身交女孩子交很多嘛
right?
对不对？
That way I'd have
因为我最主要是说
a lot of choices.
女孩子我交多的话
Right?
那我可以选择，对不对？
That's not to say
不是说我交女孩子交多的话
I'm a...
表示我这个人看起来…
... playboy.
这个人那么风流
No, not at all.
根本不是
It just means
因为我交多…女孩子交多的话
I'd have more choices.
那我可以选择
But my wife
因为我终身我爱
will be the love of my life.
就是我老婆
You didn't find anyone suitable
那以前相亲的对象
amongst them?
都没有合适的吗？
No.
都没有合适的
Why not?
为什么？
No one was suitable.
最主要是个性不合
Personality clash.
最主要是个性比较…
With all of them?
可是全部都这样吗？
Or do you have some specific...
你是不是有对女生特别有什么…
... ideal in mind?
特别有什么…要求？
So it's hard to find the right one.
不然过去你说你相亲六、七次
The main thing is
最主要就是说
some women...
这当中有些女孩子
are rather materialistic.
她本身就是说
They really are!
她喜欢物质享受，有没有
You know what I mean?
你懂意思吗？
When I take them out,
因为我每次跟她约会的话
they want to go to
她都喜欢往餐厅
expensive restaurants.
往高级方面去跑
Every day. Every meal.
每天、每餐都要吃好嘛
I think what they love
那我想说她爱的话
isn't me, the husband,
不是我这个，比如说这个丈夫
but material luxuries!
她爱什么？物质享受
Well... I see them as failures
所以说，算起来
and interesting experiences.
也很失败、很好笑
Mr. Wang, if...
王先生，如果…
If your wife...
如果你的…你的另一半
Yes, my wife...
嗯，另一半
ask you to quit betel nut and smoking...
要你不要再吃槟榔跟不要再抽烟
Do you drink?
你喝酒吗？
No, I don't.
我…我不喝酒
Would you quit?
那你愿意配合吗？
Yes, I would.
可以
Can you?
戒得掉吗？
Yes, I can.
应该可以啊！
I'm not that addicted to
因为我本身抽烟、吃槟榔
betel nut or smoking.
不会吃得很重
I'll be fine.
没关系啦！
Miss, if you say...
那个小姐…如果说
If it's OK...
比如说可以的话
I wonder if you would...
就是说…你能不能…
... marry me?
嫁给我
Marry me, please.
啊！嫁给我
That's too fast
太快了啦！
Too fast?
太快了
Could you...
你能不能…
It's all right...we can be...
那没关系，那我们如果说…
But I mean...
但是假如说你愿意嫁给我的话
If you marry me then I can quit!
那我可以戒
It's a deal!
就一句话
How about it?
怎么样？
I promise.
我保证
Please think about it.
你考虑考虑吧！
If it's OK with you.
如果说可以的话
You don't have to answer me right away.
那你再答复我也可以
So...
那么的话
Let's drink a toast!
祝我们能够很成功
Hello.
嘿，你好
Are you...
你是…
...the girl on the phone?
电话中那位小姐吗？
My name's Tao.
我姓桃
Mr. Tao.
嘱！桃先生
Yes.
是
You have quite a history!
桃先生，你的经历很多、很丰富
Sure. Since I graduated from high school,
是啊，因为我自从学校毕业以后
I went on to Japan to study.
那么到日本去留学
First at Osaka University
首先是到大阪大学的
to become a...
生产工程的研究
manufacturing designer.
做生产工程设计
Then at Tokyo University,
然后再到东京的东京大学
I studied psychology and physiology.
读生、心理学系
Then two years of research in Shizuoka.
那么毕业以后在静冈那边
I came back to Taiwan.
研习了两年回台湾
As I worked in the international trade,
回台湾以后，从事国际贸易
I traveled around the world.
就做了周游世界各国
I've been to America, Europe,
那么也到美国、欧洲
Japan and other Asian countries.
日本、东南亚各地去
Later I went to mainland China
后来到了大陆去
when they allowed
这个台湾跟大陆
visits across the strait.
有海峡两岸的探亲
So I went to China,
返乡探亲的时候，回了大陆去了
and then...
所以说呢，再来就是说
After returning to Taiwan,
回台湾以后
I did a lot of charity work.
在台湾做了很多慈善工作
For example,
那么譬如说
I worked for a Buddhist charity.
我在慈济功德会里面当慈济人
We help our brothers and sisters
在那边为我们这个
in Taiwan.
台湾的一些同胞来服务
They are people who are in need.
为我们台湾的这些社会人士
I'm involved in good works.
再来呢，做一些行善的工作
Another job I must tell you about is
更加可向你报告的就是说
I teach singing
我在老人会里面
in a senior's home.
当那个带动唱老师
You teach singing?
带动…带动唱？
Yes.
带动唱，对！
May I sing a song for you?
我也可以表演一段给你听
OK?
好不好？
It's a nice song.
就是说，有一首歌也是蛮不错的
The song of "Everlasting Youth".
就是说，一首《长青之歌》啦！
"We say life begins at the age of seventy. "
就是说，人生七十才开始
"Eighty's not rare. "
八十不稀奇
"Ninety is a dime a dozen."
九十满街皆是
"One hundred is the season of smiles. "
一百笑咪咪
That's what I do.
这样子的一个带动唱
It makes the old folks happy.
使他们…那个…
It cheers them up.
老人有一点欢喜的感觉
So...
那…
May I ask...
请问一下
...how old are you?
那你实际年龄是贵庚呢？
I'm in my thirties.
今年三十多
Miss Wu,
吴小姐
what else should l
还有什么要来
tell you about me?
告诉你我本身的吗？
You have nothing to ask me?
你都没有问题要问我啊？
I've been doing all the asking.
好像都是我在问你
It's your turn to ask.
换你问我
I have no questions for you.
我没有什么好问的了
Excuse me, are you Miss Wu?
对不起，请问你是吴小姐吗？
Mr. Lin.
林先生
I'm sorry to keep you waiting.
你有没有等很久？
This is my name card.
这是我的名片
You're a Scorpio.
天蝎座
Scorpio!
天蝎座！
Scorpios tend to be proud and aloof.
天蝎座好像比较孤傲一点
People say that
很多人都这样讲
but I don't agree.
但是我并不这样觉得
I still don't know
我现在还不知道
what you do.
你平常是做什么的？
I work in a hospital.
我在医院上班
In a hospital!
医院！
Yes.
对
Are you a doctor?
你是医师吗？
No,
不是
I'm a pharmacist.
我是药剂师
I think your shoes are very special.
我觉得你的鞋子蛮特别的
They're very pretty
蛮漂亮的
and make you look innocent.
很清纯的感觉
They're okay.
还好啦
Do you mind if I smoke?
对不起，你介意我抽烟吗？
Well...
奇怪！
Aren't you curious about me?
你对我都不会有一些好奇啊？
Sorry about the smoke.
烟太多了，不好意思
You...
你…
I think your shoes are really
我觉得你的鞋子很特别
really special.
真的很特别
You're really into shoes.
你很喜欢注意人家的鞋子暖
Yes.
对对对
Do you mind if we play a game?
我们可以玩一个心理游戏吗？
A psychological test
心理游戏
about shoes.
跟鞋子有关的心理游戏
All right.
可以啊！
This suitcase...
你看我这个箱子里面
It's full of women's shoes.
这里面全部都是女生的鞋子暖
Yeah, women's shoes.
对，全部都是女鞋
You brought it with you?
这是你刚带过来的？
Yes.
对…
Do you want to play the game?
有没有兴趣玩一下这个游戏？
How?
怎么玩？
I put a shoe on you
我帮你换鞋子
and see how you respond to it.
然后测试你对这个鞋子的反应
I don't think it's a good idea.
这样子不太好吧！
It's OK.
没关系啦！
Let's give it a try.
好啦！我们来试一下
You can't judge a person
你不能因为你喜欢什么样鞋子
based on his reaction to a shoe!
就知道这个人的心理
I bought this one in Paris.
这是巴黎买的鞋子
If it doesn't fit,
那万一不合
would you think
你不是觉得我心理有问题？
No, I wouldn't.
不会啦！
Let's give it a try.
我们试一下，好不好？
It's fun, right?
吴小姐，好玩嘛！
Try it! I bought it in Paris.
试一下，这巴黎买的
We'll attract attentions.
这边很多人耶！
They can't see us in here.
这一间人家看不到
Besides,
而且我在这里
no one will see me under the table!
桌子下根本不会有人看到
Come on, try it!
来啦，试一下
Wow! It looks so special on you!
哇靠！很特别啊！
Want to try another pair?
要不要再试一双？
Come on, try another one.
没关系啦！
Miss Wu...
吴小姐…
It's eleven thirty in the evening.
现在是晚上十一点半
Thursday night.
今天是星期四
It's time for me to call you again.
我该打电话给你的时间又到了
I'm fine.
但是我没事
Anything you'd like to tell me about?
你有没有事情要跟我说
Professor Lo.
罗教授
Are you looking for furniture?
来逛家具啊？
Well, my wife wants to look around.
对！没有，是我太太要逛
And the kids want to go to McDonald's.
然后小孩子要吃麦当劳
I'm tagging along.
就陪他们出来
How are you doing?
你过的怎么样？
Why are you still single?
你怎么还没有结婚啊？
I haven't met Mr. Right.
找不到对象，没有人要我
That can't be true! You're too choosy.
不会吧！条件太高了
No, I think I just haven't met Mr. Right.
不是，你就是觉得你碰不到啊！
Some seem okay.
你也会觉得有一些人不错
But when it comes to marriage...
可是结婚，然后你要跟他…
... it doesn't feel right.
你就觉得好像不是这样子
It's really hard.
就是找不到
You haven't met anyone suitable?
难道一个好的都没碰过吗？
The good ones are all taken.
好的都是别人的
That can't be true.
不会啦！
You should broaden your frequency range.
把你的频率放宽一点
What do you mean?
什么意思？
If you set a very narrow range,
如果说你把自己的条件
Iike when you tune a radio...
就像我们要去…
Hello? May I ask...
你好，请问一下，你…
May I ask...
请问一下
What do you do?
你现在目前的工作状况是什么？
Is she the one?
是不是那一个？
Looks like it.
好像是耶！
That's her, right?
应该是她吧！
Have you brought anything
你有没有带什么
that proves you're 28 years old?
什么东西可以证明你二十八岁？
No.
没有耶！
No?
没有？
Well...
嗯
How old are you?
那…那你几岁？
I'll give you one last chance.
我再给你一次机会
All right.
好，我跟你讲
I'm seventeen.
我十七
Seventeen years old?
十七…十七岁？
I can't believe he told her!
亏他讲得出来
Sometimes I'd get dead drunk.
有时候茫茫，有时候喝得烂醉
Once...actually several times...
有一次，有几次比较离谱
I ended up sleeping in the street.
就会睡在路边这样子
But usually I'd remember that
但是大概就是说
I have to go to work the next day,
平常会想到说明天要上班
and it keeps me
所以说，也不至于
from drinking too much.
让自己醉到什么程度这样子
In addition to drinking,
那你除了喝酒
you must have other hobbies?
总该有些什么别的消遣吧！
Well...
就是…
Apart from drinking,
除了喝酒以外
I like watching adult movies.
我最喜欢看A片
You know what? It's really fun.
你知道吗？看A片有很多乐趣
Once I came across an old movie
比方说，有一次我看到一支
starring Ai lijima.
饭岛爱的旧片子
It was really interesting.
那个很鲜
She was still very young.
那时候饭岛爱还很年轻的时候
She looked so tanned.
然后，那时候她已经晒得很黑了
There is a beach scene.
然后在海边…
She is strolling with her boyfriend
然后在海边就很好玩
on the beach.
她就跟她男朋友在海边散步
They are walking along.
然后散步，走走走
Suddenly three guys turn up
忽然就来了三个人！
and they take hold of her!
三个人就把她押着
It was a very powerful scene!
有那种很冲击性的
It made me so excited.
让我看了，我觉得很刺激
There are other kinds-like S&M.
那另外还有那种，像SM的啊
S&M means sadomasochism.
所谓SM，就是虐待的
The sadist is the attacker
S就是施虐者
while the masochist is the victim.
M就是被虐待的那一个人这样子
There are different genres.
那当然还不止啊！
They are shot in different ways.
那当然他们拍摄的手法很多种
Each kind gives me
看每一种不同的片子
a different sensation.
就是给我不同的感觉
Actually, if it's possible,
其实我心里是想说
I wouldn't mind
如果有机会的话
making one myself.
我也想拍一支片子看看这样子
Can you understand?
你能了解吗？
Do you believe that I can tell fortunes?
你相不相信我会算命？
Can you?
你会算命？
Yes, I can.
对
Give me your right hand.
把你的右手给我
Right hand.
右手！
I see that the time's not right
其实你的姻缘还没到
for you to marry.
你不应该那么早结婚
You have many things
人生还有很多很美好的事情
to enjoy first.
可以去尽情享受
Look at this.
你注意看，你注意看
What it tells is...
它其实这种整个感觉来讲的话
...in your previous life,
基本上
your marriage was too perfect.
因为你的前世姻缘太好了
So in this life,
这一世可能不太适合结婚
marriage isn't right for you.
你懂我意思吗？
But in our society
可是，我们在这种社会
the pressure is always on
你一天到晚想到说
getting married.
我要征婚、要结婚什么
You shouldn't give in to it.
我觉得对你来讲并不是好事
When should I get married then?
那什么时候适合结婚呢？
I think marriage...
我觉得结不结婚…
Marriage is just a formality.
结婚只不过是一个形式而已
What I have in mind is very simple.
我的心态其实很简单
We met each other
我们今天
under such circumstances.
因为这样一个方式而认识
I'm sincere
那我有这个诚意
and I believe you are, too.
我相信你也有这个诚意
Or you wouldn't have placed the ad.
要不然你也不会登报纸
So how do we advance to
那怎么样去让我们的关系
the next step?
能够更密切一点
This is what I want to say.
我觉得这是一个我所要
No need for
我觉得那些繁文褥节
unnecessary formalities.
不要去想那么多
My idea is simple, direct,
我的观念很简单、很单纯的
and sincere.
而且很诚恳的
I believe that
你看我的眼神
you can see it in my eyes.
应该可以感觉的出来
Although...
虽然…
we met under such circumstances...
我们是经由这样的方式来认识的
you really impress me.
但我对你的感觉真的很好
But how can you...
可是，你怎么能…
Can you rely on
就是说，你真的能靠第一个感觉
your first impression
你就可以知道说
to know whom to marry?
这个人是你结婚的对象吗？
Whom to marry?
结…结婚的对象？
I....
我…
Yes, I am looking for a husband.
对啊！我是征婚啊！
Actually...
不是，我其实…
I...
我讲那么多啦
What I've been trying to say is...
其实我最主要的目的是要告诉你
Actually, we don't...
我觉得其实我们不必去…
We don't have to bother
有很多事情它不是
with such formalities.
一定要经过一些程序来…
You know what I mean?
你了解我的意思吗？
You and l,
就是说，你…
we know each other, right?
我们两个认识嘛
You're a woman and I'm a man,
你是女生，我是男人
we can...
大家可以…
Do you get it now?
你现在可以了解我的意思了吗？
I don't know what you're talking about.
你在说什么，我听不懂耶！
What I mean is...
我的意思就是说，我…
to be honest with you...
其实，我坦白跟你说
Today I came here,
就是我今天来这边
I want to meet a girl.
我希望认识一个女孩子
You've left me
那你给我的感觉非常好
with a really good impression.
真的很棒的一个感觉
I really...
那我真的…
I might as well say it.
我这样讲好了
My purpose is....
我的目的就是我希望…
I want to make love to you.
跟你MAKE LOVE
You know what I mean?
你了解我的意思吗？
Make love!
做爱！
I think
在我的观念认为
it's only natural.
这种事情真的蛮平常的
Here we are.
其实如果感觉到了
We should give it a try.
我觉得不妨试试看
In our society...
因为今天的社会…
But I feel nothing for you.
但是我对你没感觉
Between men and women...
其实这种男女之间的事
the feelings will come
可能做了以后才会有感觉
Don't you think that's a bit too easy?
你不觉得你这样很随便吗？
You pick a girl off the street.
你随便在路上找一个人
You think she's nice
觉得感觉不错
and then you want to sleep with her.
你就要跟她上床
But I have my principles.
但我还是会有我的原则
I have my principles
我是有原则性的选
about whom I sleep with.
就是有原则性的上床
She has to be good enough for you.
还要你看得上？
Well, that's it.
应该就是这样子吧！
Because...
因为这种东西…
Why don't you just get a prostitute?
那你为什么不去找妓女呢？
I hate the idea.
我最讨厌那种感觉
Because when you're through with her...
因为你知道，你跟她做完了
you have to pay her and that feels bad!
然后要付钱，那种感觉很差
So you want a free prostitute?
所以，你是要找一个免费的妓女
No, not really.
不是…这个…
I've waited several days
因为我也等了那么多天
to meet you...
好不容易跟你见了面
Like waiting for your prey.
你等了那么多天，等到一个猎物
You shouldn't put it like that.
这个话不能这么说
Look, let me be frank with you.
因为我坦白告诉你好了
I'm thirty-five, married,
我三十五岁
with a child.
我结过婚
So what? No big deal!
我有一个小孩
I'm still out there
又如何呢？又怎么样？
Iooking for what I want.
我还不是照样出来找我想要的
Marriage certificate is
这种盖个章、签个名而已嘛！
You can't take it seriously, can you?
你不会那么认真吧！
Maybe you're right.
也许你讲得都对啦！
But...
但是…
I'm talking from my experiences.
我只是告诉你说有一些经验嘛
Look at the news.
你看报纸、报章杂志
Stories about unhappy marriages every day.
每天都是婚姻哪里不幸福
I think we should stop this discussion.
我觉得我们可以停止这个话题了
You don't have to...
你这么说，我…
All I can tell you is that
反正我只能告诉你
I am really sincere.
我真的很诚恳地
Very sincere in my offer!
很诚意地邀请你啦！
I think this is a...
我觉得这种…
very romantic place.
对不对，在这种很浪漫的地方
But we can find
那我们可以
an even more romantic place.
再找一个更浪漫的地方
Check, please!
小姐，买单！
Check.
小姐
Come on...
不是…
Miss, the Check!
小姐，买单
I want you to see how sincere I am.
我只想表达就是说我很有诚意
You check!
先生，你买单好了
The taxes you pay
你付的税金
control our lives.
就是在控制我们的生活
And the politicians control the taxes.
那政治是在管这些税金
I want to ask.
我想发问
I want to know your real motives.
我想了解你真正的动机
Let me introduce myself...
自我介绍
I'm the president of the Hsin Mei Corporation.
我是欣美股份有限公司的负责人
Quite rich!
那么有钱
Yes, there are many opportunities.
虽然说是有很多机会啦！
Actually l...
其实我…
Yes, I haven't done much
虽然做的事情很少
but...
可是都…
Today I went to meet the men
我今天还是乖乖地
as I planned.
去跟那些男人见面了
Every day I take the same bus
每天坐一样的公交车
to the same teahouse.
去一样的地方
It feels like going to work.
好像上班
Back then
只不过以前来的是病人
I treated my patients.
我可以帮他们医病
But for these men...
可是现在来的那些人
No matter how sincere they are,
就算他们跟我掏心掏肺的
there is nothing I can do for them.
我也觉得无能为力
Each time I see them,
每次看到他们的时候
I think of you.
我还是会一直想到你
I don't mind you not answering the phone.
你不接电话没关系
Just let me talk.
只要让我讲就好了
As I did before.
就像以前一样
Tell you what happened
跟你报告
in my life.
我一天所有的事情就好了
You might think I'm crazy.
你可能觉得我这样
Talking to your answering machine
对着录音机喋喋不休的讲
Iike a mad woman.
像个神经病一样
But if I don't...
可是，如果我不这样的话
I think
我想
I really will go nuts.
我真的会变成神经病
I'm advertising for a husband.
我在征婚
Advertising?
征婚？
Wow!
哇！
See how determined I am?
够有决心了吧？
Any results?
那征婚的结果呢？
Haven't found the right one yet.
还没选到
I think it's my problem.
我觉得是我自己的问题
It's not that they're not good enough.
不是他们不够好
I haven't opened up myself yet.
是我的那个门还没有打开
But I'll try.
可是，我会努力的
Is that relationship really over?
那段感情真的结束了吗？
You and your ex...
那你跟之前的…
Can I ask you something more personal?
可不可以问你比较深入的问题？
Hello?
哈
It depends.
看看啊
Did you sleep
你跟你之前的男朋友
with all your boyfriends?
都有发生过关系吗？
Well...
那你…
It's my turn to ask.
可以轮我问你了吗？
Go ahead.
好，你问啊！
But I haven't finished with mine.
可是我的问题还没有问完
So?
有吗？
All right, I'll put it another way.
好，那我换个问题问你好了
Do you do one night stands?
一夜情你接受吗？
No.
不接受
You think that's...
你会觉得那个是属于…
Chia-wen! Over here!
哈！佳雯！这里
Sit down.
坐啊！
This is Miss Wu.
吴小姐
She's my assistant.
她算是我得力的助手
Sort of secretary.
也算我秘书之一
One of my secretaries.
秘书之一
Is it taken care off?
怎么样
How is it going?
还可以吧？
Yes.
办好了
Just a minute.
等一下
Hello.
口畏
Yes, I'll ask her to come over.
好，我会叫她过去
You talk to her then.
你跟她讲好了，好不好？
Here.
找你电话
You don't do one night stands.
你不能接受一夜情
What business are you in?
请问你是做什么行业的啊？
You said you would tell me when we met.
因为那天你说见面再谈
I think...
我觉得…
I'm a freelancer.
我现在的工作算自由业
What kind of freelancer?
什么样的自由业？
What kind of freelancer...
什么样的自由业啊！
If I told you,
如果说我今天
you could earn a lot of money...
可以让你赚更多钱
Would you do it?
你愿意吗？
What kind of work do you do?
你到底是做什么工作的？
To be blunt, it's...
直接了当讲的话，是属于…
in the line of the high-class...
走高级路线的…
sex industry.
性生活交易
If I told you...
如果说我今天…
Excuse me.
对不起
You're not into it?
你不会接受？
Have you ever considered it?
有没有想过，有没有考虑过？
This is ridiculous!
你真是太荒谬了！
My ad is very clear!
我报纸上面写的是…
I'm... Iooking for
是要…是要…是要…
a husband!
是要征婚
I am looking for a... right!
我是要找一个…对！
But I just...
可是，我刚跟你说了嘛
Why do you doubt what it says in the ad?
你怎么会怀疑我上面的那个…
I don't. No.
我不是怀疑，我不是怀疑
No? What are you here for?
不是！那你今天来的目的？
I want to get married, too!
当然我想，目的！
Of course I do.
当然，征婚啊！
I want to get married!
征婚啊！
But if you need money...
可是你如果有经济上面
I can help you with that.
我也可以帮助你
That's impossible for me!
我不可能！
Listen, I've met lots of people
我跟你讲
especially women...
人我可是见多了，尤其是女人
Nothing is impossible!
世界上，没有什么不可能
If you can think differently,
脑袋转过来的话，什么都可能
But never mind.
好，没关系
Here's my card.
这我的名片
If you change your mind...
当你有可能的那一天的时候
give me a call.
你打电话给我好了
Bye.
拜拜！
Mr. Chou,
周先生
can I ask you a few questions?
我可以问你几个问题吗？
Go ahead.
你说啊！
What made you think...
你为什么…
because I put up an ad...
你为什么认为我登报征婚
you have the rights
你就有权利来问我这些问题呢？
I don't know how to answer that.
你这个问题我不知道怎么回答你
A personal ad means
登报征婚
we can get to know each other.
当然就要互相了解
But what on earth...
可是你凭什么…
You know nothing about me.
你根本不知道这个人
Nothing about my background,
她的生活背景
my past...
她的来历、她的过去
or anything else.
她的所有东西
And you assume that I would...
你就认为她会要去做这些事情
Then you want...want to...
然后你要来…来…
No, no, wait a minute!
不不不，等一下
No.
不是
What is your rationale?
你凭什么会要来试这些事情呢？
My rationale? There's none!
凭什么？我没有凭什么呀！
I am looking for a wife.
我是来征婚啊！只是问问看
But there's no harm asking!
看有没有刚好机会碰到
Just in case.
这样子而已
But the point is...
不是，你刚刚问的问题都是…
you ask a woman to be a prostitute.
都是要找一个女人去做妓女嘛！
Do you need to put it like that?
你需要把它讲的那么难听吗？
I feel...
我觉得…
But that's the business you're in.
你在做的事情就是这样
What made you think...
我…我为什么要让你觉得…
I think you're prejudiced.
我觉得…我倒觉得你观念很奇怪
You discriminate people.
为什么奇怪？我觉得你歧视
All professions are equal, right?
职业是不分贵贱的，对不对
A prostitute...
做妓女…
as you call it...
就像你讲的
OK, call her a prostitute.
名词是叫妓女好了
So you look down on her?
你会瞧不起她吗？
Because of people like you...
就是因为有你们这些人
I think it's because people like you
我是觉得倒是就有你们这些人
that they are looked down on.
被你们这些人瞧不起
My point is...
我的重点是…
in your eyes any woman
在你们的眼里任何女人
can become a prostitute, right?
都可能会变成妓女吗？
Do you try this with every woman?
你通通都试吗？
No harm asking, right?
问问看倒无所谓
You behave like an animal
你就像个动物一样
asking every woman if she'd go with you...
到处去问人家要不要跟你
Not with me.
不是跟我
I think you're over-reacting.
我觉得你的反应是太大了一点
If you don't want to do it,
你不愿意就算了嘛！
it's not a big deal.
没什么了不起的
If I get a job
那下次我看我
in the presidential palace,
如果说我到总统府上班的话
I'll ask you to join me.
我再介绍你去好了
That should be good enough for you.
这样比较高级一点
Hello, sorry I missed your call.
口畏，这里是
Please leave a message
请留话
Please pick up the phone.
你接电话好不好？
I'm sick!
我生病了！
I feel so awful.
我好难过
Have you gone back to your wife?
你是不是回到你老婆那边去了？
Please pick up the phone.
你接电话好不好？
One hundred and fifty.
一百五
Thanks! -Thanks!
谢谢！一谢谢！
What troubles me most is...
其实，我现在很大的困扰是说
I made up my mind to do something.
我常常已经决定要做一件事情
And it's the right thing to do.
然后我也觉得这样做才是对的
It's the right thing for me.
是对我比较好的
But I just can't do it.
可是我做不到
I can't make it.
就是我决定了，可是我做不到
I feel that I can't make it.
我觉得我没有能力做
You don't get it?
不懂？
Well...
好，就是说…
For example,
比方说
I feel...
我…我觉得
it's very painful
我跟这个男生在一起的时候
when I see him.
有些东西是很痛苦的
So I think
所以，我觉得
I should put an end to it.
我应该要结束这样子的关系
But when I don't get to see him,
可是，当我没有跟
the pain is even worse.
我觉得更痛苦
It all boils down to your choice.
一切都是选择
Choose what you can endure.
选择你所能承受的
Mr. Yu, was it you who called me?
喻先生，你前天打电话给我
Yes, it was me.
对，是我打的电话
I didn't know you'd bring your father.
没有想到你会带你爸爸一起来
Actually, it's him
其实这一次征婚的对象是我爸爸
who's looking for a wife.
不是我！
Go on.
继续讲
But you...
可是你…
But how about your mother?
你母亲…？
My mother has gone living abroad.
母亲啊…母亲她已经出国了
She may never come back.
她可能也不大想回来了
Because...
因为…
She is a modern woman.
她比较新潮
She prefers what life abroad can offer.
她喜欢外国比较…物质各方面
I'm sorry.
不是！
I don't quite get it.
我没有太明白您父亲的意思
I mean...
就是…
your mother has gone abroad, right?
你母亲是出国了，对不对？
Right.
对，对
She's gone, but she'll be back, right?
她出国了，她会回来对不对？
It's pretty unlikely.
应该就不会回来了吧！
Unlikely?
应该？
Yes.
对！
Unlikely, but if she does come back...
应该？那如果她回来了，对不对
If she does, then we'll be in trouble.
她回来了，那就粮了！
So...
这…可是这…
You get a lot of phone calls?
随时都有很多人要找你？
Uh, yes.
也不是，就是
People are always calling me.
对！随时有可能有电话
Miss Wu, you're nearsighted?
吴小姐…近视眼？
Yes.
嗯
How serious?
几度？
Quite serious but they're for astigmatism.
五百多度，不过我这个是散光
Why is that?
为什么呢？为什么要这样？
Because contact lenses
因为隐形眼镜不能够配散光的
You wear a contact for nearsightedness
就是里面是隐形眼镜，近视的
and glasses for astigmatism?
外面是散光的
Right.
对
You are nearsighted, too. How serious?
你也是近视嘛！几度？
I'm...
我这个…
I'm astigmatic.
我是散光
My right eye is nearsighted
但是我是右眼近视，左眼散光
It's really a pain.
你知道，很麻烦的
Mr. Ho,
何先生，我觉得你…
there's something weird about you.
你怪怪的耶
Me?
我怪怪的？
Yes.
对
What do you mean?
什么意思？是说…
My manners
我样子怪怪的
or my looks?
还是我的人怪怪的？
It's just everything
不是，我觉得你整个人
about you.
都给我感觉怪怪的
Well, I guess
我想，可能是因为跟我的职业
maybe it has to do with my profession.
有一点关系吧！
Do you know what I do?
你知道我是做什么的吗？
No, Sorry, I forgot.
对不起，我忘了
But you look like a fortuneteller.
可是，看你的样子很像算命的
Really?
真的假的？
Yes.
对！
A fortuneteller?
像算命的？
You know what? I'm a painter.
我是画画的，你知道吗？
A fortuneteller...
像算命的
I mean, you could be a painter, too...
没有…也可以像画家啦！
May I order a drink?
那个…我可以点东西喝吗？
Of course.
可以！
Excuse me.
对不起，对不起
A beer, please!
小姐，啤酒，谢谢
Hello, hello.
口畏，喂…
Sorry.
对不起
Mr. Ho, your leg...
何先生，你的脚…
Anything wrong with it?
你的脚有问题吗？
Yes. I have a bad leg.
对啊，我的脚本来就有问题
What about it?
怎么样？
When you walked over there,
可是你刚刚走过去的时候是踉着
And then you weren't.
然后…然后又不踉了
When you walked back,
然后回来的时候又踉着耶！
I always walk with a limp.
哪里，我一直踉着的啊
No, you don't.
没有
You were talking and getting excited.
你刚刚在讲话，然后好像很激动
At that point, you seemed fine.
那时候你就变正常了
Really?
真的假的？
I wasn't limping
我刚讲电话的时候没有踉
No, you weren't.
对啊！
And I think
而且我觉得你的胡子
your beard is fake, too.
也是假的耶
My beard!
胡子！
All right! You're right.
好啦！好啦！对啦！对啦！
My leg is fine.
我的脚，我没有踉啦！
But I thought
可是我的出发点是，我想如果说
if I came as a disabled person,
我今天是一个残疾的人士
I met you
然后如果我跟你碰了面
and you could accept that...
然后你还愿意跟我交往
you would be a very special girl.
你一定是个很值得交往的女生
That was what I thought.
这就是我的出发点
But my beard is real.
我的胡子，我这胡子是真的啊
You look very familiar to me.
我觉得你很面熟耶！
Really?
啊！
Me... familiar?
我很面熟？
Yes.
对！
You look familiar to me, too.
我也觉得你有一点面熟耶
No, I mean,
不是，我的意思是说
I've seen you somewhere.
我觉得我看过你
And I recognize your voice, too.
而且，你的声音我也听过
I went to Ching Hsin Elementary School.
静心小学的，你什么小学的？
I went to Fu Hsin.
我是复兴
You could be a classmate of my cousin's.
你可能跟我表弟同学
Maybe I met you
会不会是什么我以前
when I visited my cousin!
去找我表弟的时候碰过你
OK, I've gone too far.
这个太扯了
So I look familiar...
对啊！面熟！你知道
But you know we artists...
你知道，我们艺文界的人士
From time to time,
有的时候也是要
we appear on TV.
应邀上一些谈话性的节目
Maybe it's possible that...
所以…所以可能是…
You should stop lying.
我觉得你不要再骗人了
I know I've seen you before.
因为我觉得你的样子，我…
I've seen you
我看过你
in all those different roles.
而且我觉得我看过你很多的造型
In various performances.
就是各式各样的
So in my mind...
在我的脑海里面，所以…
All right.
好啦！好啦…
So you found me out.
对，所以你知道嘛！
I'm an actor.
对，我是一个演员
Sorry, it's so hot.
对不起，好热！
Do I really look like a fortuneteller?
我真的看起来像算命的啊？
The hat must have given me away.
一定是这个帽子害的
Do you know my name?
你知道我名字吗？
No, I haven't....
不是，我很久…我
My surname is Niu.
我姓钮
Doze Niu!
钮承泽！
Yes.
对…
I've seen you in the movie, Growing Up.
我看过你的电影《小毕的故事》
Is that right?
嘱！是嘱？
You were a kid then.
那个，恋爱晴！
I went...
我那时候有去看
Did you like it?
很久以前，好不好看？
I liked it
很好看，可是你很久没有拍戏了
but you haven't acted for awhile, right?
对不对？
I don't think I've seen you...
不是，因为我好像…
What are you doing now?
那请问你现在是…
I'm still acting.
我一直在演，你都…
I guess you don't watch much TV.
所以你都很少看电视
See my hand?
比方我的手啊！
I was in a Hong Kong movie
我就是最近在拍一个香港电影
with Andy Lau.
跟刘德华一起
I hurt my hand then.
我手就是那个时候受伤的
You know...
你知道，那非常…
We were filming at the night market.
我们那天是在士林夜市拍戏
I was playing Andy's sidekick...
然后…然后我跟刘德华演伙伴
We were investigators...
我们是调查局的
It was really crowded.
然后就是…很多人
The killer was about to strike,
杀手要杀他，我就跑过去救他
Then...whoops!
然后…哇！很滑
Mr. Niu.
钮先生
Yes?
怎么样？
This is ridiculous.
我觉得很荒谬耶
What?
怎么样？我这个…
You feel bored?
觉得很无聊
No.
不是
Of course, it's ridiculous.
对啦！荒谬！
It's a movie.
我是觉得还好，拍电影嘛！
We have to finish shooting.
拍电影最重要，戏总要顺利拍完
Besides, I felt very honored...
而且，我觉得蛮光荣的啊
No, not your movie.
不是，我不是说你的戏
I mean
我是说…
our meeting here.
我是说你跟我约在这边
It's ridiculous.
我觉得很荒谬耶
Why?
为什么呢？
Because I'm looking for a husband.
因为我是要找一个结婚的对象
You don't want to get married...
你…你又不结婚
Then...
然后…
Wait a minute.
等一下！
You're here to make fun of me.
你在跟我开玩笑吗？
No, I'm not.
等一下，我没有在跟你开玩笑
What I want to say is...
我跟你讲这个原因是…
I do want to settle down.
我其实真的很想安定下来
You know what?
你知道吗？
Excuse me...
对不起…
Hello!
喂！
That's right, I'm in Tianmu.
对呀！我在天母，你不要…
Your girlfriend?
你女朋友打来的啊？
Yes, she's a nuisance.
对，很离谱
She keeps asking me what I'm doing.
你知道，她就问我在干嘛
She keeps calling me.
前面一通电话也是她打来的
I told her I was with friends.
然后我说我在跟朋友聊天啊
And she hung up on me.
生气，挂我电话
Then she called again.
OK，刚又打来
Mr. Niu, l...
钮先生，我…
I want a more settled life.
我想找一个比较安定的生活
I don't think your lifestyle
然后我并没有打算
would suit me.
要跟…就是演艺圈的人有什么
Your life is too complicated.
因为我觉得
It's OK. I just...
没关系，我只是…
Hang on...
不是…其实
People say our lives are complicated...
演艺圈大家都觉得很复杂
But in fact...
但是你知道，其实…
Your girlfriend's waiting for you.
你女朋友在等你
That's all right.
没关系
I can leave you my number.
或者我把我的电话留给你
I've got your number.
我有你的电话了
Oh, right.
对…
Where do I pay?
在哪里买单啊？
Let me.
我买就好了
No, I'll do it.
没有…我来…
I suppose you're meeting other people?
那就…你还有人要见嘛！
Take care.
你好好的
I should stop limping!
我干嘛还要装踉脚？
I was wondering
因为，我在想说一个女孩子
what kind of woman
到底是怎么样的一个女孩子
would take such an action.
她会有这么大的一个动作
Putting a personal ad in not only a paper
去征婚，而且是登报纸
but a major one.
而且是大报
A major newspaper.
还有点大
I was thinking,
那我会想说
"ls she an ugly girl"?
是个很丑的女生吗？
That would make sense
那还可以理解
but you're not ugly at all.
可是我觉得你很好啊
Well...
还好啦！
I can't tell that myself.
我自己没有这种感觉
Has the ad been there long?
征婚征很久了吗？
Quite a few days, right?
有几天了吧！
Yeah, a few days.
嗯，有几天了
How about the people you've met?
前面那些人怎么样？还好吧！
They're OK.
还好
All men?
都是男的？
Of course.
当然都是男的啊
I'm looking for a man.
我要找的当然是男的！
Of course they're all men.
对，都是男的
Have you had any experience?
你以前有经验过吗？
What experience?
什么…什么经验？
Experience like mine.
类似像我这样的经验
Experience with somebody like me.
像跟我这样的人的经验
Have you?
你有经验过吗？
I mean
有一种经验，是这样子的
have you ever thought about
就是说…你有没有想过说
the unhappy relationships you had.
是不是之前你那些不愉快的经验
Unhappy relationships?
不愉快的经验
Have you ever wondered
那，你有没有想过说
why the relationships made you unhappy?
这些不愉快的经验是为什么
Was it because of your personality?
难道只是因为你的人
Or his?
或是因为他的个性
Or maybe it was because of the gender?
有没有是因为性别的原因？
The gender?
性别？
...could be the cause.
的原因
If you haven't tried it,
因为你没有试过嘛，你不晓得
you wouldn't know, would you?
对不对？
What haven't I tried?
什么东西没有试过？
Don't get nervous.
你不要紧张，你不要紧张
I don't want to make you nervous.
我不想让你紧张
Can I be blunt?
我…我可不可以…
Can I ask you a personal question?
我可不可以大胆地问你一个问题
Sure.
好，你问呀
Are you...a man or a woman?
你…你是男的还是女的？
Because... -Good.
因为一好！
I'm sorry. -Good.
对不起！一很好！
I was waiting for you to ask that.
其实我在等你问，你知道吗？
I feel you are so nervous.
因为我一直觉得你好像很紧张
No, it's because...
不是，因为你…
I'm sorry...
对不起
It's okay.
好，没关系…
Don't be nervous.
你不要紧张
It's really nothing!
没有关系，真的没有关系
No, because I get the impression that...
没有，因为你给我的感觉就是…
I'm a woman!
像女的！
I think it depends on
其实我觉得应该是
how you see it.
看从什么样的角度吧！
No, l...
不是，我…
Depending on from which angle
什么样的角度去看
you make your judgment.
怎么样去评断说
So you're a woman.
所以你是女的
Am I a man, or a woman?
是男、是女？
If you say so.
其实，如果你要这样说也可以
I have the characteristics of a woman.
我有女孩子的特征啊！
But I'm looking for a man.
可是我要找的，是一个男的
I'm a man.
我是男人呀！
What I'm looking for is
我要找的是…
a "real" man.
特征是男人
You can think about it.
你可以想一下
No! I'm not one of you...
不是！因为我知道我不是你们…
Sorry, I'm not saying lesbians are...
对不起，我不是觉得说同性恋…
I have nothing against lesbians.
因为，我也不排斥同性恋
But I want a man.
可是，我要的是一个男的
I'm not a lesbian. I like women!
我不是同性恋，我喜欢女孩子呀！
But you're clearly lesbian.
你怎么会不是同性恋？
I'm not and I like women.
我不是同性恋，我喜欢女孩子
You're a woman, and you like women.
你是女的，然后你喜欢女孩子
Of course you are.
你当然是同性恋啊
You're lesbian!
你怎么会不是同性恋
I'm sorry. I...
对不起，我…
Actually many people have told me that.
其实很多人跟我讲过同样的问题
But like what I just told you
就我刚跟你说过
things aren't either black or white.
就很多事情
But for me...
可是，在我的观念里面
There is a gray area.
它是有中间地带的
You're either a man or black...
不是男的就是黑的
Sorry, no, either a man or a woman...
不是…不是男的就是女的
Either black or white. As simple as that.
不是黑的就是白的，就是这样子
How do you know if you don't try?
其实你不试试看，你怎么知道呢？
You've never tried it before, right?
你从来没有试过嘛，对不对？
But I don't want to try.
我并不想试啊
I know what I want.
因为我很清楚我要的东西是什么
Why don't you try men?
那你为什么不试试看男的呢？
I mean, give men a try.
不是，那你为什么
Men are not bad!
男人蛮棒的啊！
There's something in your hair.
你头发有个脏东西
It's OK. I'll get it.
没关系，我自己来
I'm sorry.
对不起嘱！
Higher than most people.
你的耳朵好像长得很高
My family said my ears
对，我小时候我们家里人都说
were higher than my eyebrows.
我耳高过眉
So it seems...
好像是这样子…
Yeah, it's a sign of intelligence.
对，这种人比较聪明
Your ears are higher than
你的耳朵好像
your eyebrows, too.
也比你的眉毛高一点
You're talking about yourself!
你在说你自己
You're very smart.
你很聪明
I think I respond to things quicker
我想，大概是反应有时候
than most people.
会比别人快一点点
I'm a salesman. I sell
我是做推销员的
personal protection devices.
推销防身器
Our company has many products.
我们公司产品很多
Just think about it.
因为你想想看
You may be mugged
我们常常会碰到一些
or robbed at any time.
抢劫啦、枪击啦
Raped or kidnapped for ransom
尤其是强暴、勒索
and all sort of crimes.
还有绑票，层出不穷
It's like when you're watching a TV drama
就好像你看广告一样，对不对？
and bang, a commercial comes in.
电视剧看得好好的，广告就来了
We don't have to put up with it,
这种生活
do we?
难道说是我们应该过的日子吗？
So I think...
所以我是觉得，万一…
Let me ask you frankly.
我很冒昧地问你一句
How could you protect yourself?
万一你碰到的时候
This is a mace-type spray.
这是喷雾式的防身器
A combination of chili
这是用辣椒跟芥末的
and mustard.
混合气体制成
It's not the chili you cook with
辣椒不是让你做麻辣锅
nor the mustard for your sashimi.
芥末也不是让你沾生鱼片
Just press lightly and spray.
这只要轻轻一按、一喷
Careful! Don't worry.
小心！不要紧
There...
这个…
So many bad people are out there.
是你的朋友不及外面的坏人多
But don't get scared.
不要紧，不要害怕
Look at this shock stick.
你看看，这个大四节伸缩电击棒
It is adjustable and very light.
大四节伸缩电击棒
You can handle it with one hand.
单手可以操作
Even if a robber has an axe or a blade,
不管歹徒拿的是开山刀、弹簧刀
a sword or a chopper,
倚天剑还屠龙刀
you just press this trigger.
你只要按一下这个扳机
Don't be afraid!
不要怕，不要怕
This is an 80,000 volt stunner.
这个是八万伏特的高电压
80,000 volt!
八万伏特的高电压
Even the mosquitoes get zapped.
连蚊子看了都要闪第一
So do the flies.
苍蝇看到掉眼泪
It'll send the robbers
歹徒碰到马上要送医
It's a bargain.
这个价位很便宜
It costs $8,000.
大概是八千块钱
I can give you a discount.
我可以给你打个折扣
It's really useful.
其实很管用
You may wonder what a stunner is.
也许你要问我什么叫高电压
Right?
对不对？
This is called "The Demon".
你看看，这个是大精灵
It has two switches.
大精灵，你看，这边有两个开关
A safety and the "on" switch.
一个是保险，一个是开关
Don't be afraid...
不要怕…
This one is a 200,000 volt stunner.
这个是二十万伏特的高电压
200,000 volt.
二十万伏特的高电压
When it touches the robber,
歹徒只要碰到的话
his four limbs will fall off immediately.
马上四肢无力，五体投地
He'll be stunned out of his wits.
六神无主，七上八下
This costs only $3,500.
这个价位只有三千五百块钱
A small price
三千五百块钱
for peace and safety.
是买个平安、买个保险
I recommend this one in particular.
我要跟你特别推荐
This is called "The Tracker".
这个叫做追踪防身器
It has a special...
追踪防身器它这个是按照
A specially designed grip.
人体工学设计这个把柄
Easy to handle.
非常好握
It won't harm you.
来来来，我不会害你的
It took a Canadian policeman
这是一位加拿大警官
7 years to invent it.
研发七年而成功的
Once you spray the dye
它这里面的颜料，喷出去以后
his face will be covered with it
它可以让歹徒在脸上
Iike a mask.
跟戴了个面具一样
His eyes will be totally blinded.
他的眼睛完全看不到你
And this one here, look...
另外，你看看，这把是…
Hey, don't press it!
这个不要碰！
I'm sorry. -It's OK.
不要紧，对不起，没关系
It's alright... I'll sort it out.
我自己想办法，我自己想办法
Excuse me...
对不起，对不起，我…
No, what I mean is...
不是，我的意思是说
Your voice seems different from others.
你的声音
Different?
不太一样？
Of course.
对，那当然口罗！
That's my job.
我的工作是这样子
I'm a voice actor.
我很会控制我的声音啊
I can speak in all kinds of
我可以让我的声音听起来
different voices.
跟我本人完全不一样
That's how I earn my living.
这才是我吃饭的本钱啊！
Why did you put an ad in the paper?
你为什么会想要来征婚啊
You look pretty good to me.
你条件不错呀！
Should there be a reason?
征婚一定要有原因吗？就是…
Of course.
有啊！可能是
I'd have thought
在我来想象中
it's for old people.
会征婚的人都是年纪很大
But you are not old.
你不是
Maybe you have been hurt...
受了打击
I don't know.
那我不知道是不是啦
Or you have some illness?
还是你有什么隐疾？
I want to get married.
我想结婚
You want to marry, so do l.
你想结婚，我也想结婚
My life feels empty.
我很空虚啊
I always speak for other people.
我的工作让我每天帮别人说话
I don't like it.
我觉得很不舒服
So that's why you're here.
所以你才会来这里啊
Yes.
对啊！所以想看看
I want to see what kind of girl you are.
你是个什么样的女孩子啊
To meet people outside my circle.
我想跟圈外的人交往
Not bad, you seem gentle and quiet.
嗯，不错！看起来蛮文静的
Exactly the kind of girl I'm looking for.
我是要找一个这样子的女孩子
I talk all day long.
因为我每天都在说话
I talk and fidget a lot.
所以我会很不安，我很脂噪
I'm looking for a quiet girl
我想找一个很…
who can calm me down.
很安静的女人，可以稳定我
She'd listen to me and put me at ease.
可以听我说话，可以让我放轻松
But if you're talking all day long,
可是你不觉得
shouldn't you...
你的工作已经一直在说话
You're such a lovely girl.
像你这么可爱的女孩子
Why are you so serious?
为什么要这么严肃呢？
I'm not.
我没有很严肃啊
You're not?
你没有很严肃
You are not at peace with yourself, right?
那你是很不安！是不是？
You're so sharp. You must read a lot.
你好厉害，你有看书嘱！
It has nothing to do with books.
这不是看不看书，这是…
What then?
这是什么？这是什么？
You can't tell, can you?
说不出来了吧！
I can tell that
对不对，我告诉你
you feel very insecure.
你其实还是很不安
It's not that I can't tell....
不是说不出来，是…
It's because you're very insecure.
是…是你很不安
Cool.
酷！
It's not that. I feel very...
我没有很不安，我…我觉得很…
I can tell it from your body language.
因为看你的动作呀！
Look, you keep touching things
你看你摸摸东西，抓抓头发
You keep fidgeting.
然后人动来动去
It's a sign of insecurity.
这就是很不安的…
No, it's not.
这不是很不安，这是…
Are you aware of your insecurity?
你没有安全感，你知道吗？
That's why you're looking for a husband.
所以你会来征婚
You want someone to look after you,
你要找一个可以好好的照顾你
to protect you.
保护你的人
Have you found one?
那…那你有找到这样子的人吗？
No.
没有
I...
我…
I'm still looking.
我在找呀！
That's my point.
对呀，所以说啊
I've met many people.
我认识很…我现在认识了很多人
I'm still looking. I'm trying hard.
我在找，我在努力
Cool.
酷！
So cool. Very cool.
很酷，很酷
I'm trying hard to find the right person.
努力地找一个这样子的人
So I say I'm the guy
所以啊，我觉得我就是
who can give you security.
要给人家安全感的人
You think you can?
你觉得你可以给人安全感
You're even wearing sun glasses.
你还戴着墨镜
I can't even see your eyes.
我连你的眼睛长什么样
I wear them all the time.
这是我的习惯耶
I feel secure with them on.
我觉得戴墨镜
No need to look anyone in the eyes.
你可以跟人隔离
That proves you're insecure as well.
所以你也没有安全感啊！
I just don't like
因为我不喜欢直视别人的眼睛
I think it's kind of rude.
我觉得那是一种很不礼貌
But the eyes are important.
可是眼睛很重要
They tell you
一个人说不说谎
whether one is lying or not.
或是任何情绪都可以在眼睛
This discussion is getting too serious.
我们谈这个太严肃了
We want to be partners not opponents.
我们是来征婚，不是来吵架嘛
You're a lovely girl.
你是很可爱的女孩子，干嘛呢？
Why do you need to be so defensive?
我们俩讲话…针锋相对
No, l...
不是，我…
I don't think I'm insecure.
我不觉得我很不安
Aren't there women who do dubbing?
你们不会有不同的女人去配音吗？
But they're strange.
可是那些人你会觉得很奇怪
You know...
你知道吗？
Can you do a few lines?
那你配几句给我听听看
A few lines?
配几句给你听听看
What do you think I am?
喂，你把我当做什么？
An acrobat?
杂耍的？
When you meet a clown,
你认识一个小丑
would you say to him,
你会不会叫他…
"hey, do somersaults"
口畏，翻两个跟斗
or "play a few tricks for me"?
跳几圈让我看看
It's not what I meant.
我不是那个意思，我只是…
Maruko, stop fooling around.
小丸子，你不要再到处玩
Have you finished your homework yet?
功课写了没有？
I bet you haven't.
一定没写完
Your teacher will call me tomorrow.
到时候明天老师又打电话给我
Go do your homework!
我告诉你，进房去写功课
Miyuki, we have to work hard.
美雪，我们一定要好好努力
We must solve the case
为了我爷爷的名誉
to save my grandfather's honor.
我们一定要破案才行
I can do all sorts of strange voices.
还有，很多奇怪的声音
Look, I can do this.
或者是这样的声音我也可以
Miyuki, we must work hard
美雪，我们一定要好好努力
in order to...
才能够…
Maybe I'm not the right man for you.
我可能不是你要找的对象
And you're not suitable for me.
你也并不适合我
Why don't I just admit it that
我是不是应该干脆承认
this isn't the right way to find a partner.
这样是找不到对象的
I'm just trying to
我只是在转移自己的注意力
to ease the pain you left me.
转移你带给我的痛苦
Today, a guy asked me
今天有一个男人问我说
if I was seeking revenge?
小姐，你是不是在报复
Am l?
我有吗？
He said our meeting was only
他说，你跟我见面
an opportunity for me to reject him.
好像就只是为了来嫌弃我
Or like what Sisy Chen told me.
还是像陈文茜说的
I can treat the whole process
我可以把征婚
as a ceremony.
当做一种重要的仪式
I saw her in a restaurant the other day.
我那天在餐厅看到她
I wanted to know
我想知道
what she'd do if she was in my shoes.
如果她是我，她会怎么办
I've been thinking...
那我在想说，如果
If you don't regard time
你不把时间想象是一种静止的
For example,
比如说，你想象自己
imagine yourself
是一个写剧本的人
as a scriptwriter...
或者你想象你
Or imagine that
是一个导演的时候
you are a director...
你就会想说这个故事
Then you know that
其实是会再发展的
a story can be developed.
时间不是停留在那一刻
Time doesn't stop at any precise moment.
因为时间不是停留在那一刻
Since it doesn't stop
还会发展
you'll see what happens
你就可以看到说还会有很多后续
in the later development.
在那些后续过程中
In that case, you won't feel
你可能就不觉得
that particular moment is so important.
静止的那一刻那么重要
You look at the world as a whole.
而是世界的全部
It won't stop
好像是全世界的那一刻
for your tears.
而必须要去重视那一颗眼泪
You know it's only a process.
你会知道这只是一个过程
Moreover, you may discover...
而且，你可能还更会发现说
If you don't take the responsibility
这个悲伤呢
for your sadness...
你如果不马上负起责任来
or bear the burden yourself...
把它勇敢的承担起来
You think you had hurt someone...
你以为你是一个刽子手
Actually you'll hurt him
结果反而你将来
more in the long run.
其实是给对方伤害更深
The pain will last longer.
挫折更长
So if you have come to
所以如果你有这样一个
realize this,
理性的一种认识的时候
you'd be brave enough to deal with it.
当然你在处理时刻会比较有勇气
But I feel that
不过，像你刚刚讲的
from what you just said,
我会觉得说
you're the one who takes the initiative
比较是你想要结束这样的关系
to end the relationship...
就是说，你是采取一种主动
It's not you who cries.
流眼泪的好像是别人
No, not really.
那也不一定啊
For example,
比如说，可能是对方
he's the one who wants to end it, right?
希望要结束对不对？
In that case,
那对方希望要结束，包括你自己
you're forced to accept it.
如果你是一个被结束的人的话
You should follow my advice.
那你更需要这样
But you'd say you feel so miserable.
你说！这刻我很惨啦
There are two ways.
那有两种方法
Normally
比如说有一种方法
I'd tell people this...
在台湾我常常教人家就是
You feel desperate
你觉得你很’渗
so you want to kill yourself, right?
那你最好就去自杀对不对
But before you do yourself in...
那你自杀的时候
Go watch a funeral ceremony
你只要开车去台湾
anywhere in Taiwan...
任何一个在街上要办的葬礼
You'll see
你看那个葬礼
how ugly the curtains are.
外面布帘那么丑
How awful the coffin looks.
然后棺木那么难看
How ugly you'd be dressed.
每个死的人都穿那么难看的寿衣
And the terrible funeral music!
法号吹得真是吓死人了
That'll make you realize
你就会发现，还是苟活比较好
Your pain will be eased to some degree.
所以，你的悲伤就会被局限
So you...
就是帮乐器行带乐器进来
Yes, the company runs the business.
对…是公司在运作
There are many people in the office.
公司还有很多别的人
But they know nothing about
是刚好因为他们都不太懂乐器
They're businessmen.
他们只会做生意
So you help them choose?
你就是去帮他挑就是了
Yes.
对…
What else do you do?
还有呢？你还有做什么？
Have you ever worn
那穿护士服
a nurse's uniform?
你没有穿过护士服吗？
No?
没有？你都没有？
You like women in nurse's uniforms?
你很喜欢看女生穿护士服吗？
Yes.
不错啊！
They look nice in the uniform.
那个看起来不错
They look so innocent.
好像蛮纯洁的样子
I don't mean they're not innocent
也不是说不穿就不纯洁啦！
What the hell am I talking about?
乱七八糟！
Where do girls like to go?
女孩子都喜欢去哪里玩？
It depends.
不一定
I think...
我觉得…
...girls often end up
很多女生到最后
following the guys.
都是看男生喜欢去哪里玩
Really?
真的吗？
Yeah.
嗯！
What if he's into something weird?
那他如果玩那种
How weird?
多奇怪？
To be honest with you,
不瞒您说，我很喜欢到…
Here it is!
就是这个啊！
Let me show you first.
我先打给你看
Press this. Here.
你就是按这一个，这一个
Hit it like this.
打那个地方
Harder!
用力！
Let me.
我来，我来，我来
You've got to watch the back.
你要看到后面，这个要我来
Come on.
‘决，快
Come on!
快点，快点
Can you tell jokes?
你会说笑话吗？
Jokes!
笑话！
The funniest joke is...
可是我最好笑的就是…
At this point,
这一阵子最需要最轧的一个票
all I need is about...
大概是…
six or seven hundred thousand dollars!
六、七十万就差不多可以解决
Do you wear a nurse's nu-niform?
那你穿护士服吗？
Nurse's nu-niform.
护士服，护士服
Nurse's U-Nl-FORM.
[X '，护士服
Nurse's NU-lN-FORM.
户四湖！
168cm tall.
一百六十八公分
And she must look cute and sweet.
其实长相大概就是娇甜一点
That'd suit me better.
我是觉得这样子
I am his mother.
我是他妈妈
Shouldn't he know
我觉得他应该自己知道
when he wants a drink?
什么时候要喝水
And when he doesn't?
什么时候不要喝水
He does. He's just too nervous.
他知道，只是今天出来太紧张了
Give the glass to Mama.
杯子给妈妈，杯子给妈妈
Good boy.
乖，杯子给妈妈
Mrs. Cheng, I think he...
郑太太，我觉得他…
What do you think of him?
你觉得他怎么样？
What do you think?
怎么样？
Let me put it this way...
这样说好了
Do you think
你觉得他有
he's fit for marriage?
有能力结婚吗？
Marriage!
结婚！
I think he is.
我想他应该可以结婚
Really?
为什么？
He can't even look after himself.
他连照顾他自己都没有办法
How can he...
他怎么可能
I'm looking for someone to look after me.
我是要找一个照顾我的人
He can look after people.
他很会照顾别人的
He's just too nervous today.
今天是因为太紧张了
He's so used to
他只是习惯把自己的精神状况
Iiving in the world of his own.
放在一个比较…
Then he's fine with himself.
那就让他自己就够了啊
Why do you want to marry him off?
你为什么一定要让他结婚
People must marry.
人一定要结婚，人是群居的动物
But only people who are competent
可是结婚是两个人
should get married.
要有能力的人才能结婚
He is competent.
他有能力
It's just that
但是他，因为他…
he lives in the world of his own.
活在一个自己的世界里面
If there is some kind of switch
如果有一个开关，开启对了
Perhaps you could be that switch...
也许您就是那个开关
You mustn't say that...
你千万不要这样说
I don't think so.
我不认为我有这个能力
Besides...
而且…
He's just...
他只是…
... a little...
他只是比较…
You could give it a try.
你可以试试看
Try to be his friend.
你可以试试看跟他做朋友
Or just be with him.
或者是观察他一下
He's not used to the outside world.
因为他不习惯外面的世界
We get along well.
他跟我生活得很好
He even shares
他甚至可以让我去
his spiritual life with me.
跟他一起享受他的精神生活
He can look after himself.
他可以自己照顾自己
Mrs. Cheng.
郑太太
Take it easy.
不要紧张
Are you nervous?
紧张啊？
Relax. We're here for coffee.
放轻松，我们是来咖啡厅的
It's okay. Mom will drink it later.
阿南，没有关系，妈妈待会就喝
He wants me to drink, see?
他要我喝，你看
It's all right. Mom will drink it later.
没关系，妈妈待会喝
Mom will drink it later,
好，妈妈等一下喝
all right?
好不好？
He wants me to drink.
他要我喝水，他觉得我…
He probably thinks I'm too nervous.
他大概觉得我太紧张了
No one is perfect.
我想每一个人
Maybe you think he's sick
也许你认为他有病
but I don't.
可是我不认为他有病
I didn't say he's sick.
我没有说他有病，好吗？
But, I think...
不过，我想…
I suggest you shouldn't do it again.
我也建议你下次不应该这样子
Alright, I understand how you feel.
好，我知道你的感觉
But should you be willing...
不过，我希望如果说
Maybe you can think it over.
或者是，你回家想一想的话
Maybe you can be his friend.
你可以考虑跟他做朋友
Let's forget about getting married.
我们不要谈结婚
Just be friends.
就可以做朋友
Try to enter his world.
试着进入他的世界里头
We Chinese always talk about "ching".
其实我们以前中国人
The character "ching" has two parts:
“情”，情字我们看这个字
One means "heart", the other means "green"
“情”从心、从青
The color green...
青是什么？绿色！
We all agree that
绿色给全世界感觉
"green" signifies life or rebirth.
都是一种生命或者再生的
So when we say the word "ching",
所以当我们讲“情”的时候
it means something ongoing
其实是一种循环的
not something that burns out quickly.
它不是一霎那烧掉的
It involves consideration,
它是包含了很多的
responsibility and care.
关心、体谅、责任
Love has no responsibility.
爱是没有责任的，爱是一种本能
For example, love is sex.
譬如说，爱是一种性
It's biologically driven.
它是生物的、直接的、动物的
But "ching" entails commitment
而情就必须要有更多的承担
and consideration.
更多的体贴
I'm Yu Wen, you're...
我是余文，你是…
My name is Wu...
我姓吴，我是…
How do you do?
你好
You're really thirsty.
你很渴嘱？
No, usually I bring my own...
不是
When you meet these guys,
你跟这些男生碰头，都是…
who pays the bills?
饮料小吃的钱谁付？
Sometimes they do,
有时候男生会请客啊
sometimes we go Dutch...
然后有时候各付各的
I can pay for it.
我可以付啊
I have a good impression of you...
我现在对你印象很好
Thank you.
谢谢！
Let me tell you about myself first.
我…这样子好了，我先自我介绍
I mean, let's not waste time.
不是，我说我不浪费时间
I don't want to go on and on.
因为我想不能讲很多、很长
I'll tell you straight.
我直接说我的条件给你听
All the good and bad things about me.
我的优点、缺点
The good thing is
我的优点就是…
I'm very good!
我很好！
I mean I have a good heart.
不是，就是心很好
Yes.
嗯
That's the truth. Really.
千真万确，真的
It's hard to boast about yourself.
优点比较难讲，缺点就是…
Bad things are easier to talk about.
缺点比较好讲，我的缺点就是…
First of all,
第一个，我比较…
I'm kind of a loner.
孤僻！
I thought about it all night...
我昨天晚上已经想了一个晚上
In fact,
怎么讲…
I've been thinking about it
其实我已经想了十几年了
More than twenty years!
想了二十几年，我现在四十五岁
I'm somewhat reclusive.
比较孤单，就是说
Like after work, I go home
常常我在家里面，下了班以后
and I'd just sit there daydreaming.
我就会坐在那边发呆，发很久
Sometimes I think of something...
有时候是烦，有时候是累，可是
What do you do?
你是做什么工作的？
I teach Chinese in an elementary school.
我在小学教书，教国文
I'm often lost in daydreaming.
发呆的时候也不是想什么事情
I'd sit there for a long time
就是坐在那边坐很久
as still as a bonsai.
像个盆景一样不动
I can't be like this after I get married.
那我想过，结婚这样子不好
If you were my wife, I would have to...
假如说你是我老婆，这样子不是…
But I'm trying
我最近在改
to become more outgoing...
让自己比较活泼一点，比较…
My students like me.
学校的学生也很喜欢我
They say sometimes I'm quite funny.
说我有时候很风趣
The other thing is I'm thrifty.
那第二个缺点就是，我比较节省
Thrifty...stingy!
节省，小气！
People think I'm stingy.
小气是别人说的
But... I'm not really stingy!
可是我…其实我不是小气
I...
我是…
...just got used to it.
习惯！
I do spend when I need to.
该花钱的地方我也会花
Well, I'm influenced by my mom.
其实我的习惯是受我妈妈的影响
My mom is thrifty
我妈妈很节省
because our family was poor.
那是因为我们家以前过过苦日子
Then my parents had become used to it.
后来我爸、妈就变成习惯了
I thought if she alone was thrifty,
那我觉得她一个人节省有点…
she'd feel lonely.
孤单
So I became thrifty to keep her company.
所以我觉得我可以陪她一起节省
My parents live in the south.
我爸爸、妈妈现在住南部
They're in their eighties.
他们八十多岁
They're old and hope I'll marry soon.
年纪很大，蛮希望我赶快结婚的
I would like to marry,
我自己也很想结婚
have a child and a family of my own.
想生个孩子，有一个家…
I didn't want to get married
我以前不想结婚是因为我…
because I thought that life was too fragile.
我觉得生命很脆弱
The thought of aging and dying of illness
就是说，什么生老病死
was unbearable.
我很不能忍受
If my wife, my child, my family....
假如我老婆、我孩子、我的亲人
became old and sick and dead,
老了、病了、死了、分离了
I would feel...
我觉得…
it's too much to bear.
会伤心，所以我觉得很残忍
Now I'm getting older...
那我现在年纪比较大了
Getting...
比较…
I've changed.
改变了！
I'm able to accept these things.
可以承受这些东西了
So I've said it all.
现在…我现在讲话到这里
So now...you know
到这个时候
all good and bad things about me.
我的优点、缺点讲完
What do you think?
你对我的意愿
Can we be friends
就是说跟我在一起做朋友
or something closer?
或说我们俩可以配
What do you think?
意愿有多少？
I haven't thought about it yet.
我还没想耶！
I'm so sure of my feelings for you.
我对你是百分之百
You haven't even heard me speak.
你在那么短的时间
And you're so sure of your feelings?
你就百分之百
I know what I'm talking about.
因为我不是睁眼说瞎话，我不笨
I can see you're very...nice.
我已经看到你很…为什么很好
Very nice.
你啊！
How do you know?
我为什么很好？
You have a pretty forehead.
对，你的额头很漂亮
You can see that from my forehead?
你看得到我的额头？
It looks very intelligent, very dignified.
你的额头很聪明，然后很端庄
And your eyes are like a child's.
然后你的眼睛像小孩子
They're smiling
然后好像眼睛会笑
and full of wonder.
好像会好奇很多事情
They look pure.
很干净
And you...
然后你的…
...you smiled twice.
你刚刚已经笑了两次了
Your smiles are so sweet.
你的笑容很甜
Have you heard a song called,
你有没有听过一条歌
"Everlasting Smile"?
一条歌叫做“永远的微笑”
My father used to sing it
以前我爸爸
while courting my mother.
追我妈妈的时候唱的一条歌
"My love..."
心上的人儿
"Feel not sorrow nor dejection"
你不要悲伤
"l wish only that your smile, "
愿你的笑容
"Goes on forever. "
永远那样
The last line is really great!
尾巴这四个字棒极了
A very simple line.
好简单的四个字
Yet it conveys so much emotion.
然后把好大的情感给讲出来了
Your forehead looks like my mother's.
你知不知道你的额头很像我妈妈
Mine is like my dad's, a bit broad.
我额头像我爸，比较高
It's very hard
而且很硬，以前我的外号叫铁头
It makes a noise when you hit it.
打起来很响
Very loud noise.
好响，好响
It didn't hurt at all.
不痛，一点都不痛
Not at all.
一点都不痛
That's how I used to bully my classmates.
小时候我就这样欺负同学
Can we be frank now?
可不可以现在我们直接…
Can you say whether you would be
说…那句话，就是…
willing to be with me?
你愿不愿意跟我…？
I mean you don't have to meet
我是说
any more men after this.
不要再跟其它男生去碰头了
Or if you do meet them,
要碰头的话
tell them to go away.
你就随便讲讲打发掉
Don't you think
你不觉得你现在就这样要求我
this is a little too sudden?
太快了吗？
But life is short.
因为人生很短
But you just said
对啊，可是你刚刚都说
you spent over twenty years
你花了十几二十年
deciding whether to get married or not.
去决定一个你要不要结婚
And now...
那…
We've only spent ten, twenty minutes.
我们才十几分钟、二十分钟吧
The bad things about me aren't really bad.
我的缺点其实不是缺点
They're just my habits.
是我的习惯
My characteristics.
就是说，等于是特色
I can make changes, too.
也可以改
If you want me to change, I can...
假如你喜欢它怎么改，我就…
But I have no such plans.
可是我并不打算要去改变
If you think I'm stingy...
你看我节省的话
If you want a new dress
假如你要买衣服，你要吃西餐
Whatever you say, l'd...
你要…你要花什么钱，我都…
If I want to buy a new dress
如果我要用你一个月的薪水
with your month's salary?
买我一件衣服呢？
Of course you can.
当然可以！
Are you sure?
你确定吗？
I really want to take you
我实在很想拉着你的手
to meet my parents.
让我爸妈看到你
How happy would they be!
他们一定会很高兴
I always meet these men here.
我都约在那家餐厅耶
Where we came for our first date.
我们第一次约会的地方
I choose different tables
我会根据每天不同的心情
and who I'm meeting that day...
不同的对象，选择不同的位子
But no matter where I sit,
但是，不管我坐在哪里
I always feel secure.
我都可以感觉很安全
I can become another person
我可以变成另外一个人
and hide my real self.
把自己藏起来
My only fear is
我唯一害怕的是
if one day
如果有一天
you walk in all of sudden,
你突然走进来
what should I do?
我要怎么办？
It was raining really hard that day.
那天雨实在是下得太大了
I was riding my bike.
我骑摩托车
A bus went pass.
被开过去的公交车
I got splashed and soaked through.
溅起来的雨水淋得全身都湿湿的
I didn't want to meet you like that.
我想我自己的情况那么不好
So I didn't come up.
所以我就不敢上来了
Have you always been so timid
你一直都那么谨慎
and unsure of yourself?
然后对自己那么没信心？
Actually, I spent time in jail.
其实我坐过牢
I was inside for a year and a half.
我坐过一年半的牢
Are you surprised to hear this?
我这样讲你会不会吓一跳
It had nothing to do with me.
也不是都是我的原因
My father was passing bad checks.
我爸犯了票据法
He couldn't pay back the money, so l...
一年内拿不出那么多钱， 所以…
I hope you aren't put off.
希望你没有吓到
I worked as a mail inspector
我在监狱的时候
while I was in jail.
是替人家检查信件的
I looked well-behaved.
因为我看起来比较乖
So I was asked to check the mails.
所以长官就叫我去检查信件
I read people's letters every day.
每天看人家的信，真好笑
I got to know their secrets.
看人家的秘密
I was engaged before I went in.
之前我有未婚妻，已经订婚了
But she left me soon after.
我坐牢不到半年就跑掉了
I don't blame her.
也不能怪她
Everyone wants to marry a decent guy.
谁都希望嫁到一个好的
Do you tell this
你是不是认识每一个女生
to every girl you meet?
都会马上就告诉她
About...
你…
No.
没有，没有
It's not something I'm proud of.
这种事情不是很光彩的
Then why did you tell me?
那你为什么会告诉我？
I didn't want to waste your time.
我不想浪费时间，我就直接讲
I had gone out with a few girls.
因为之前我认识很多女朋友
I didn't tell them at first.
我都没讲
But when I did tell them,
但是后来我跟她们讲之后
they...started to avoid me
她们就…打电话也说很忙
and gradually disappeared.
要不然就说慢慢再联络
So I thought...
所以，我觉得…
I feel something for this guy.
这个人
I think our relationship
我觉得我跟他的故事还没完
would not end in this place.
不会结束在这家餐厅里
What makes me feel this way
我这样感觉
isn't his looks
不是因为他的长相
or his frankness.
不是因为他诚实
He had this strange smile.
而是因为他那奇怪的笑
It looks like my own.
跟我一样
A smile of awkwardness
笑的好像很尴尬
and helplessness.
很无可奈何
Surely you can understand it.
我这样讲，你应该懂吧
Others may not but you definitely can.
别人可以不懂，但是你一定懂
But what should I do with him?
接下来我应该跟他做什么呢？
He suggested we could go fishing.
他建议我们可以去钓虾
But I thought we should
但是我觉得
sleep with each other.
我应该跟他上床
Do you know how scared I was?
你知道我很害怕吗？
I was so scared.
我真的很害怕耶！
It was the first time
我第一次觉得医院那么可怕
Lying on the operating table...
当我躺在那个手术台的时候
I really prayed for the courage
我真的…我真的希望
to keep the baby.
我有勇气把他生下来
But I didn't.
可是我没有，没有生他
So heartless of me.
我就是很逊
Where were you then?
那个时候你在哪里？
Where were you?
在哪里？
Do you know I get so scared
你知不知道
every time I come home?
我每天回家都很害怕
Like I just said.
就像我刚刚跟你说的
Honestly,
我可能一直也做不好
these things I'm telling you to do...
虽然我会讲，我很清楚
I probably couldn't do myself.
我可能一辈子也做不到
Choose what you can endure
就是选择你所能够承担的
and move on.
就往前走
But I've endured so much pain!
可是承担的很痛苦啊！
Pain makes you rise above everything.
有痛苦、有冲突，才能够超脱啊
If everything goes smoothly,
如果你一辈子都活得平平顺顺的
you'd never grow up.
怎么会有成长
Actually...
就像…
I'm not really attracted to women.
我其实并不喜欢女人
What do you mean?
什么意思？
I like men.
我其实比较喜欢男人
I knew this from a very young age.
这一点我从很小我就知道
But I also knew
但是从那个时候开始
I wanted to lead
我就决定我要做一个正常人
a "normal" life.
过最普通的生活
You're not saying this just to console me?
你不会是因为要安慰我
Making your life so much worse
所以你要把你自己
so I'll feel better.
弄得比我更惨一点吧！
No, what about you?
那你呢？
And your troubles?
你的困扰呢？
My life seems a bit better than yours.
这样好像比你好一点
Are you Mr. Wang?
请问你是王先生吗？
Is that Miss Wu?
你是吴小姐吗？
Yes.
嗯
Can you help me? I'm Mr. Wang.
那麻烦你带我好了，我是王先生
Can I take your arm?
我拉你的手肘好了
Sorry.
不好意思
Have you been waiting long?
你等很久了吗？
That's all right.
还好
Here. Please have a seat.
到了，这边请
Thank you.
谢谢，谢谢
Mr. Wang, your eyes...
王先生，你的眼睛是…？
My eyes? -Completely?
我啊？一完全…
Yes, completely blind.
对啊！就是全部看不到
Were you born blind?
是先天还是…？
Yes.
从小生出来就看不到
Did the doctor say anything about it?
有医生告诉你什么病因
Atrophy of the optic nerve.
医生说，我视神经萎缩
Then how could you read my ad?
那你怎么会看得到我登的启事？
I didn't.
我根本就是没有看到
My friend told me about it.
是我朋友告诉我的
And I gave you a call.
然后我就打电话给你了
I am sorry.
抱歉，不好意思
What do you do
你平常除了作音乐
apart from being a musician?
就没有再做其它的事
Nothing really.
没有呀！
But sometimes if I need extra money,
我有时候为了钱，歌卖不掉
I'd go busking in the pedestrian tunnel.
会在地下道唱唱歌
The tunnel?
地下道？
Yes. You probably gave me money before.
对啊！说不定你还投过钱给我
You just don't remember.
你都不知道
Which tunnel?
在哪一个地下道？
Any tunnel.
在哪一个地下道呀！
Next time maybe you'll see me there again.
下一次你自己…
Please be generous!
记得多给我一点钱
I don't think your name is Wu.
我觉得你好像不姓吴耶！
It is Wu.
我姓吴啊！
Your surname is Tu, isn't it?
你姓杜，对不对？
Don't you recognize me?
认识我吗？
Do I look familiar?
你觉得我面熟吗？
Several years ago, you treated my eyes.
几年前我让你看过眼睛
You're an eye doctor, aren't you?
你应该是眼科医师嘛，对不对？
Dr. Tu.
你姓杜
Are you okay?
你怎么了？
Yes, my name is Tu Chia-chen.
对，我叫杜家珍
I'm sorry. I meant no harm.
对不起，我不是恶意的
No, I'm sorry...
对不起…
I really meant no harm.
我真的不是恶意的
No, I'm sorry I shouldn't have lied.
没有，对不起，我不应该骗你
When we spoke on the phone,
我在电话里面就觉得你应该姓杜
Why?
为什么？
I recognized your voice.
因为我认得你的声音呀！
I was your patient.
我让你看过眼睛嘛！
Your voice sounded familiar on the phone.
我在电话里面
You should be Dr. Tu.
应该姓杜，不姓吴
How could it be Wu?
为什么姓吴呢？
So I felt I must come.
所以就更让我觉得我应该要来了
But I apologize.
不过，很对不起
On the phone, I said my eyes were bad.
我在电话里告诉你我眼睛不方便
I didn't tell you I was blind.
没有完全告诉你说我看不到
Are you disappointed?
那你会不会很失望？
It's just that I didn't expect...
我只是没想到而已
Not disappointed?
你不失望吗？
I thought...
我…我想…
I didn't expect
既然我…我没有想过说
a blind person would
会来一个看不见的人
turn up and consider...
来跟我一起考虑我的…
It's natural that you're disappointed.
不过，我想失望是正常的吧！
Yeah.
对啊！
But why do you call yourself Wu?
你为什么要姓吴呢？
Isn't Tu good enough? -Actually...
姓杜不好吗？一其实…
Tu!
姓杜！
Have you got used to being Miss Wu?
你已经习惯你是吴小姐吗？
I sometimes forget.
有时候会忘记吧！
Often?
常常吗？
When you've been lying long enough...
你知道吗？说谎说久了，是…
Our eyes can never lie.
眼睛永远不能说谎
You can be Miss Wu or Miss Tu.
不像你，姓杜又可以姓吴
No disrespect intended.
我没有刺伤你的意思
I can never lie
只是我的眼睛
because of my eyes.
永远这辈子都不能说谎
My eyes are a kind of marks on me.
我走到哪里
I can never see anything.
我永远看不见，就是看不见
So I might as well not tell any lies.
所以，我想我就干脆
When you realize
那在电话里面你发现我是杜医师
I was Dr. Tu on the phone,
你发现我是一个医生的时候
weren't you afraid?
你不害怕吗？
Why should I be afraid?
我怎么会害怕，我很想要来…
I was being cheeky...
我就有一种调皮的心情
I wanted to expose you.
我想我要来揭穿
My name isn't the issue.
其实姓什么无所谓
I just wanted to be
我只是不要过去的我…
cut off from my past.
带到现在而已
But using another surname
可是你告诉人家你姓吴
as a disguise....
你甚至用一个保护色，对许多人
Do you enjoy it?
你喜欢吗？
When you've been lying long enough,
有时候说谎说久了
you'll get used to it.
是会习惯的
Is that so?
是这样吗？
But I don't enjoy it.
可是我不喜欢
Sometimes, I feel it's absurd.
我有时候也觉得很荒谬
I'm looking for a husband.
我明明是要找一个
But I can't tell him my real surname.
然后我不能告诉他我姓什么
But...
然后…
It's possible that
可是我可能会碰到
I could meet someone with whom
我真的很有可能会碰到
I'd spend the rest of my life.
一个要托付终生的人
In that case, I'm probably
这样说，你可能可以嫁给我
I think I should stop
我觉得我应该停止
meeting these men.
再跟那些男人见面了
Because I find it scary.
因为我觉得非常的可怕
Each time I meet someone,
每次当我跟他们见面的时候
without hesitation,
他们总是毫无保留地告诉我
he tells me his secrets, his desires.
他们的隐私，他们的秘密
I feel I wasn't talking to him
那种感觉不像是在交谈
but peeping through the keyhole.
好像是我在偷窥
They are always in the light.
然后，他们永远在明亮的地方
And I'm in the shadows.
我在黑暗的地方
But how do I get in the light?
可是…
Hello? -l...
口畏一我…
Hello?
口畏…
Doctor Tu?
杜医师吗？
I'm sorry...
对不起
It's me who should apologize.
应该是我对不起
I've been listening to your calls.
我一直在听你打来的电话
I should say I've been eavesdropping.
应该说是偷听
Are you Mrs. Wu?
你是吴太太？
Yes.
是
I've been back in Taiwan for some time.
我回台湾有一阵子了
I listened to your messages by accident.
不小心听到你的留言
I know it's weird
我自己心态是有一点奇怪
to let you call every day.
就让你每天打电话来
I'm sorry.
对不起
I didn't know you had come back.
我不知道你已经回到他家了
I came here after the accident.
他出事以后我就回来了
The accident?
出事？
So you don't know
所以，你真的不知道
my husband's dead.
我先生已经死了
He flew from Phnom Penh
他从金边要到越南，转机回台湾
The plane crashed in Vietnam.
飞机还没到越南就出事了
Dr. Tu, I know it's hard for you to bear.
杜医师，我知道你会很难承受
It's hard for me, too.
我一直也很难承受
But today I was determined
不过我今天决心拿起这个电话来
To tell you that you should stop calling.
就是要告诉你，你不用再打来了
He's no longer here to answer it.
他不在了，也没办法回你电话
The last time he came to me
他最后来找我
was to tell me about your affair.
就是来跟我坦白你们的事情
He told me you were pregnant
说你怀孕了，说你想生下来
I knew him too well.
以他的个性，他敢来跟我讲
It took a lot for him to tell me this.
他是下了很大的决心了
He kept apologizing
他一直跟我认错
but he was adamant.
可是他相当地坚决
I cried. So did he.
我哭，他也哭
He left very early next morning.
第二天一早，他就搭飞机走了
After the accident, I was full of hate.
事情发生以后我很恨
I hated him and I hated you even more.
恨他，更恨你
How could you bring such disaster
你凭什么把这么大的灾难
to my family?
带到我们家里
He was willing to give everything up
他又竟然会为了一个
for the sake of a woman
我见都没有见过的女人
I'd never even met?!
他什么都可以不要
After the first message,
我第一次听到你的留话
I hoped you'd keep calling.
就希望你可以一直讲下去
I wanted to know
我很想听
everything between you two.
想知道你们之间所有的事情
Some evenings,
有几个晚上
I sat waiting for your call.
我干脆就坐在电话旁边等
At times I was so tempted to
有时候听听又很气
pick up the phone and scream.
想拿起电话来骂
But I can't listen to you anymore.
但是我不能再听下去了
I feel...
我觉得
I'm doing something really cruel.
我自己在做一件很残酷的事情
I answered the phone today
其实我今天拿起电话
just to ask you to stop.
只是想告诉你，你不用再打来了
Fate has been unfair to all of us.
命运对我们每一个人都很不公平
At first I felt satisfaction
刚开始看你那么可怜
from your misery.
我还有一种报复的快感
But now I've calmed down.
可是我现在很平静
I know at last
我终于知道
why things happened the way they did.
事情为什么会是那样了
Listening to your messages
听你的留话
made me realize
我发现自己从来没有
I never committed myself
像你那样对他的付出
to him as you did.
我也不可能对任何人如此付出
I can't do that for anyone.
知道这个，我还有什么好怨恨的
So why should I bear grudges?
我要谢谢你，让我完全平静下来
Thank you for bringing peace to me.
可以去面对新的生活
I can now bring myself to face a new life.
吴家珍，你好
Wu Chia-chen, how are you?
我也不知道该说些什么
I don't know what to say.
这是我今天第二次留话
This is my second message today.
方便的话
If it's possible,
可不可以再跟你见个面
can I see you again?
这样就放弃
To give up now would be too easy.
好像又太随便了一点
If you don't want to contact me,
如果你不想跟我联络
I'll drop by the teahouse.
我会找时间到餐厅走走
Maybe we'll run into each other.
也许能不期而遇，也说不定